<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<ClassroomData>
  <Lesson>
    <Title>Velocity and Speed</Title>
    <Content>
      <Block>In many day-to-day circumstances, velocity and speed are interchangable words. Velocity, is the change in position over the change in time, Δx/Δt. The character delta "Δ" is the greek character for d, in the scientific community, Δ means change.</Block>
      <Block>To calculus students, this concept should be very familliar. Here's an example: if a ball moves 5 meters to the right every 2 seconds, Δx = 5 meters, and Δt = 2 seconds. Therefore, Δx/Δt = 5m/2s = 2.5 meters per second, the ball is moving at a speed of 2.5 meters per second.</Block>
    </Content>
    <SimulationData>
      <Simulation>
        <fps>60</fps>
        <g>0</g>
        <gAD>0</gAD>
        <r>15</r>
        <ObjectData>
          <Object>
            <x>10</x>
            <y>10</y>
            <r>2</r>
            <m>1</m>
            <e>1</e>
            <Color>
              <a>255</a>
              <r>32</r>
              <g>163</g>
              <b>255</b>
            </Color>
            <Velocity>
              <x>10</x>
              <y>0</y>
              <m>0</m>
              <a>0</a>
            </Velocity>
          </Object>
        </ObjectData>
      </Simulation>
    </SimulationData>
    <Content>
      <Block>Velocity is defined as Δx/Δt, average velocity, is the the displacement (change in position) over change in time. Displacement is final position minus original position.</Block>
      <Block>Speed is the magnitude of velocity, velocity has a component of direction, backwards or forward. However speed is always positive, it is the absolute value of velocity: s = |v|. Average speed is the distance traveled over change in time: d/Δt. If a car goes around a 1 mile long circle at 10 miles per hour, the average velocity of the car will be 0 mph, however, the average speed of the car will be 10 mph.</Block>
    </Content>
    <SimulationData>
      <Simulation>
        <fps>60</fps>
        <g>0</g>
        <gAD>0</gAD>
        <r>10</r>
        <ObjectData>
          <Object>
            <x>10</x>
            <y>10</y>
            <r>2</r>
            <m>1</m>
            <e>1</e>
            <Color>
              <a>255</a>
              <r>32</r>
              <g>255</g>
              <b>163</b>
            </Color>
            <Velocity>
              <x>20</x>
              <y>0</y>
              <m>0</m>
              <a>0</a>
            </Velocity>
          </Object>
          <Object>
            <x>114</x>
            <y>10</y>
            <r>2</r>
            <m>1</m>
            <e>1</e>
            <Color>
              <a>000</a>
              <r>32</r>
              <g>255</g>
              <b>255</b>
            </Color>
            <Velocity>
              <x>-20</x>
              <y>0</y>
              <m>0</m>
              <a>0</a>
            </Velocity>
          </Object>
        </ObjectData>
      </Simulation>
    </SimulationData>
    <Content>
      <Block>In the simulation above, the green ball is travelling at a constant speed of 20 u/s (units per second), however, it's velocity is initialy 20 u/s, but then changes to -20 u/s.</Block>
      <Block>Everytime that the ball return's to it's original position, the average velocity is 0 u/s because the displacement is 0 u (units). The average speed however is 20 u/s.</Block>
    </Content>
  </Lesson>
  <Lesson>
    <Title>Acceleration</Title>
    <Content>
      <Block>Velocity is the change in position over a certain length of time, what is the change in velocity of a length of time? Acceleration.</Block>
      <Block>Because acceleration is the change in velocity over a change in time: a = Δv/Δt = Δm/((Δt)^2), this means that acceleration is measured in meters per second squared: m/s/s or m/s^2.</Block>
      <Block>Obects on earth fall, when falling, an object is accelerating towards the center of the earth at about 9.8m/s/s.</Block>
    </Content>
    <SimulationData>
      <Simulation>
        <fps>60</fps>
        <g>20</g>
        <gAD>1.5</gAD>
        <r>5</r>
        <ObjectData>
          <Object>
            <x>10</x>
            <y>10</y>
            <r>2</r>
            <m>1</m>
            <e>1</e>
            <Color>
              <a>255</a>
              <r>255</r>
              <g>32</g>
              <b>163</b>
            </Color>
            <Velocity>
              <x>0</x>
              <y>0</y>
              <m>0</m>
              <a>0</a>
            </Velocity>
          </Object>
          <Object>
            <x>20</x>
            <y>10</y>
            <r>2</r>
            <m>1</m>
            <e>1</e>
            <Color>
              <a>255</a>
              <r>32</r>
              <g>255</g>
              <b>163</b>
            </Color>
            <Velocity>
              <x>10</x>
              <y>0</y>
              <m>0</m>
              <a>0</a>
            </Velocity>
          </Object>
          <Object>
            <x>40</x>
            <y>10</y>
            <r>2</r>
            <m>1</m>
            <e>1</e>
            <Color>
              <a>255</a>
              <r>32</r>
              <g>163</g>
              <b>255</b>
            </Color>
            <Velocity>
              <x>0</x>
              <y>0</y>
              <m>15</m>
              <a>-45</a>
            </Velocity>
          </Object>
        </ObjectData>
      </Simulation>
    </SimulationData>
    <Content>
      <Block>The balls above are falling at a constant acceleration of 20 units per second squared. The ball on the left starts from standstill, the ball in the center starts with an initial velocity of 10 u/s to the right, the ball on the right starts with an initial velocity of 15 u/s at a 45 degree angle upwards. The two balls on the right will have a constant horizontal velocity because they are not accelerating horizontaly.</Block>
    </Content>
  </Lesson>
  <Lesson>
    <Title>Calculating object's motions</Title>
    <Content>
      <Block>The goal of physics is to describe how things interact in nature. This means that physics employs a lot of math to calculate velocities, positions and much more.</Block>
      <Block>To find an object's velocity or position given different parameters, physicist often use calculus, however in this class, we will be using algebra and trigonometry to solve our problems</Block>
      <Block>To find the position of an object with a constant velocity at a certain time, we use the equation x = p0 + v*t, where p0 is the object's position at time 0. Finding the velocity of an object at a certain time given a constant acceleration is very similar, v = v0 + at where v0 is the original velocity of the object at time 0.</Block>
      <Block>These equations are simple but don't allow us to solve for an objects position at a certain time, given the object's acceleration, initial velocity, and initial position. This is when we use the equation x = x0 + v0*t + (1/2)*a*(t^2). This equation allows us to calculate how much an object has fallen in a certain amount of time, or how far a car has traveled while accelerating from a stop.</Block>
    </Content>
    <SimulationData>
      <Simulation>
        <fps>60</fps>
        <g>10</g>
        <gAD>0</gAD>
        <r>10</r>
        <ObjectData>
          <Object>
            <x>10</x>
            <y>30</y>
            <r>3</r>
            <m>1</m>
            <e>1</e>
            <Color>
              <a>255</a>
              <r>163</r>
              <g>255</g>
              <b>32</b>
            </Color>
            <Velocity>
              <x>10</x>
              <y>0</y>
              <m>0</m>
              <a>0</a>
            </Velocity>
          </Object>
        </ObjectData>
      </Simulation>
    </SimulationData>
    <Content>
      <Block>The object above starts with an intial position of 0 u is accelerating at 10 u/s/s to the right with an initial velocity of 10 u/s to the right; what will be the object's position and velocity when t = 5. Find the answer for this question and then find the solution below.</Block>
      <Block>Answer: At time t = 5, the object will have a velocity of 60 u/s and have a position of 175 units.</Block>
    </Content>
  </Lesson>
</ClassroomData>